THE Bennets were engaged to dine with the Lucases; and again, during the chief of the day, was Miss
Lucas so kind as to listen to Mr. Collins. Elizabeth took an opportunity of thanking her.
“It keeps him in good humour,” said she, “and I am more obliged to you than I can express.”
Charlotte assured her friend of her satisfaction in being useful, and that it amply repaid her
for the little sacrifice of her time. This was very amiable; but Charlotte’s kindness
extended farther than Elizabeth had any conception of:—its object was nothing less than to secure her
from any return of Mr. Collins’s addresses, by engaging them towards herself. Such was
Miss Lucas’s scheme; and appearances were so favourable, that when they parted at night,
she would have felt almost sure of success if he had not been to leave Hertfordshire so
very soon. But here she did injustice to the fire and independence of his character; for
it led him to escape out of Longbourn House the next morning with admirable slyness, and hasten
to Lucas Lodge to throw himself at her feet. He was anxious to avoid the notice of his cousins,
from a conviction that, if they saw him depart, they could not fail to conjecture his design,
and he was not willing to have the attempt known till its success could be known likewise; for,
though feeling almost secure, and with reason, for Charlotte had been tolerably encouraging, he
was comparatively diffident since the adventure of Wednesday. His reception, however, was of the most
flattering kind. Miss Lucas perceived him from an upper window as he walked towards the house,
and instantly set out to meet him accidentally in the lane. But little had she dared to hope
that so much love and eloquence awaited her there. In as short a time as Mr. Collins’s long speeches
would allow, everything was settled between them to the satisfaction of both; and as they entered
the house, he earnestly entreated her to name the day that was to make him the happiest of men;
and though such a solicitation must be waived for the present, the lady felt no inclination
to trifle with his happiness. The stupidity with which he was favoured by nature must guard
his courtship from any charm that could make a woman wish for its continuance; and Miss Lucas,
who accepted him solely from the pure and disinterested desire of an establishment,
cared not how soon that establishment were gained. Sir William and Lady Lucas were speedily applied
to for their consent; and it was bestowed with a most joyful alacrity. Mr. Collins’s
present circumstances made it a most eligible match for their daughter,
to whom they could give little fortune; and his prospects of future wealth were exceedingly
fair. Lady Lucas began directly to calculate, with more interest than the matter had ever
Bennet was likely to live; and Sir William gave it as his decided opinion, that whenever Mr. Collins
should be in possession of the Longbourn estate, it would be highly expedient that both he and his
wife should make their appearance at St. James’s. The whole family in short were properly overjoyed
on the occasion. The younger girls formed hopes of coming out a year or two sooner than they
might otherwise have done; and the boys were relieved from their apprehension of Charlotte’s
dying an old maid. Charlotte herself was tolerably composed. She had gained her point, and had time
to consider of it. Her reflections were in general satisfactory. Mr. Collins, to be sure, was neither
sensible nor agreeable: his society was irksome, and his attachment to her must be imaginary. But
still he would be her husband. Without thinking highly either of men or of matrimony, marriage
had always been her object: it was the only honourable provision for well-educated young women
of small fortune, and, however uncertain of giving happiness, must be their pleasantest preservative
from want. This preservative she had now obtained; and at the age of twenty-seven, without having
ever been handsome, she felt all the good luck of it. The least agreeable circumstance in the
business was the surprise it must occasion to Elizabeth Bennet, whose friendship she valued
beyond that of any other person. Elizabeth would wonder, and probably would blame her; and though
her resolution was not to be shaken, her feelings must be hurt by such a disapprobation. She
resolved to give her the information herself; and therefore charged Mr. Collins, when he returned
to Longbourn to dinner, to drop no hint of what had passed before any of the family. A promise
of secrecy was of course very dutifully given, but it could not be kept without difficulty; for
the curiosity excited by his long absence burst forth in such very direct questions on his return,
as required some ingenuity to evade, and he was at the same time exercising great self-denial,
for he was longing to publish his prosperous love. As he was to begin his journey too early on the
morrow to see any of the family, the ceremony of leave-taking was performed when the ladies
moved for the night; and Mrs. Bennet, with great politeness and cordiality,
said how happy they should be to see him at Longbourn again, whenever his other engagements
might allow him to visit them. “My dear madam,” he replied,
“this invitation is particularly gratifying, because it is what I have been hoping to receive;
and you may be very certain that I shall avail myself of it as soon as possible.”
They were all astonished; and Mr. Bennet, who could by no means wish
for so speedy a return, immediately said,— “But is there not danger of Lady Catherine’s
disapprobation here, my good sir? You had better neglect your relations than run the
risk of offending your patroness.” “My dear sir,” replied Mr. Collins,
“I am particularly obliged to you for this friendly caution,
and you may depend upon my not taking so material a step without her Ladyship’s concurrence.”
“You cannot be too much on your guard. Risk anything rather than her displeasure;
and if you find it likely to be raised by your coming to us again, which I should
think exceedingly probable, stay quietly at home, and be satisfied that we shall take no offence.”
“Believe me, my dear sir, my gratitude is warmly excited by such affectionate attention; and,
depend upon it, you will speedily receive from me a letter of thanks
for this as well as for every other mark of your regard during my stay in Hertfordshire.
As for my fair cousins, though my absence may not be long enough to render it necessary, I
shall now take the liberty of wishing them health and happiness, not excepting my cousin Elizabeth.”
With proper civilities, the ladies then withdrew; all of them equally surprised to find that he
meditated a quick return. Mrs. Bennet wished to understand by it that he thought of paying his
addresses to one of her younger girls, and Mary might have been prevailed on to accept him. She
rated his abilities much higher than any of the others: there was a solidity in his reflections
which often struck her; and though by no means so clever as herself, she thought that, if encouraged
to read and improve himself by such an example as hers, he might become a very agreeable companion.
But on the following morning every hope of this kind was done away. Miss Lucas called soon after
breakfast, and in a private conference with Elizabeth related the event of the day before.
The possibility of Mr. Collins’s fancying himself in love with her friend had once occurred to
Elizabeth within the last day or two: but that Charlotte could encourage him seemed almost as
far from possibility as that she could encourage him herself; and her astonishment was consequently
so great as to overcome at first the bounds of decorum, and she could not help crying out,—
“Engaged to Mr. Collins! my dear Charlotte, impossible!”
The steady countenance which Miss Lucas had commanded in telling her story gave
way to a momentary confusion here on receiving so direct a reproach; though,
as it was no more than she expected, she soon regained her composure, and calmly replied,—
“Why should you be surprised, my dear Eliza? Do you think it incredible that Mr. Collins should be
able to procure any woman’s good opinion, because he was not so happy as to succeed with you?”
But Elizabeth had now recollected herself; and, making a strong effort for it, was able to assure
her, with tolerable firmness, that the prospect of their relationship was highly grateful to her,
and that she wished her all imaginable happiness. “I see what you are feeling,” replied Charlotte;
“you must be surprised, very much surprised, so lately as Mr. Collins was wishing to marry you.
But when you have had time to think it all over, I hope you will be satisfied with what I have done.
I am not romantic, you know. I never was. I ask only a comfortable home; and,
considering Mr. Collins’s character, connections, and situation in life, I am convinced that my
chance of happiness with him is as fair as most people can boast on entering the marriage state.”
Elizabeth quietly answered “undoubtedly;” and, after an awkward pause, they returned to the
rest of the family. Charlotte did not stay much longer; and Elizabeth was then left to reflect on
what she had heard. It was a long time before she became at all reconciled to the idea of
so unsuitable a match. The strangeness of Mr. Collins’s making two offers of marriage within
three days was nothing in comparison of his being now accepted. She had always felt that Charlotte’s
opinion of matrimony was not exactly like her own; but she could not have supposed it possible that,
when called into action, she would have sacrificed every better feeling to worldly
advantage. Charlotte, the wife of Mr. Collins, was a most humiliating picture! And to the pang
of a friend disgracing herself, and sunk in her esteem, was added the distressing conviction
that it was impossible for that friend to be tolerably happy in the lot she had chosen.
CHAPTER XXIII.
ELIZABETH was sitting with her mother and sisters, reflecting on what she had heard,
and doubting whether she was authorized to mention it, when Sir William Lucas himself appeared,
sent by his daughter to announce her engagement to the family. With many compliments to them,
and much self-gratulation on the prospect of a connection between the houses, he unfolded the
matter,—to an audience not merely wondering, but incredulous; for Mrs. Bennet, with more
perseverance than politeness, protested he must be entirely mistaken; and Lydia, always unguarded
and often uncivil, boisterously exclaimed,— “Good Lord! Sir William, how can you tell
such a story? Do not you know that Mr. Collins wants to marry Lizzy?”
Nothing less than the complaisance of a courtier could have borne without anger such treatment:
but Sir William’s good-breeding carried him through it all; and though he begged leave
to be positive as to the truth of his information, he listened to all their
impertinence with the most forbearing courtesy. Elizabeth, feeling it incumbent on her to relieve
him from so unpleasant a situation, now put herself forward to confirm his account,
by mentioning her prior knowledge of it from Charlotte herself; and endeavoured to put a stop
to the exclamations of her mother and sisters, by the earnestness of her congratulations to
Sir William, in which she was readily joined by Jane, and by making a variety of remarks
on the happiness that might be expected from the match, the excellent character of Mr. Collins, and
the convenient distance of Hunsford from London. Mrs. Bennet was, in fact, too much overpowered to
say a great deal while Sir William remained; but no sooner had he left them than her feelings found
a rapid vent. In the first place, she persisted in disbelieving the whole of the matter; secondly,
she was very sure that Mr. Collins had been taken in; thirdly, she trusted that they would never be
happy together; and, fourthly, that the match might be broken off. Two inferences, however,
were plainly deduced from the whole: one, that Elizabeth was the real cause of all the mischief;
and the other, that she herself had been barbarously used by them all; and on these two
points she principally dwelt during the rest of the day. Nothing could console and nothing appease
her. Nor did that day wear out her resentment. A week elapsed before she could see Elizabeth
without scolding her: a month passed away before she could speak to Sir William or Lady Lucas
without being rude; and many months were gone before she could at all forgive their daughter.
Mr. Bennet’s emotions were much more tranquil on the occasion, and such as
he did experience he pronounced to be of a most agreeable sort; for it gratified him, he said,
to discover that Charlotte Lucas, whom he had been used to think tolerably sensible, was as foolish
as his wife, and more foolish than his daughter! Jane confessed herself a little surprised at the
match: but she said less of her astonishment than of her earnest desire for their happiness;
nor could Elizabeth persuade her to consider it as improbable. Kitty and Lydia were far
from envying Miss Lucas, for Mr. Collins was only a clergyman; and it affected them in no other way
than as a piece of news to spread at Meryton. Lady Lucas could not be insensible of triumph
on being able to retort on Mrs. Bennet the comfort of having a daughter well married;
and she called at Longbourn rather oftener than usual to say how happy she was, though
Mrs. Bennet’s sour looks and ill-natured remarks might have been enough to drive happiness away.
Between Elizabeth and Charlotte there was a restraint which kept them mutually silent on
the subject; and Elizabeth felt persuaded that no real confidence could ever subsist between them
again. Her disappointment in Charlotte made her turn with fonder regard to her sister, of whose
rectitude and delicacy she was sure her opinion could never be shaken, and for whose happiness she
grew daily more anxious, as Bingley had now been gone a week, and nothing was heard of his return.
Jane had sent Caroline an early answer to her letter, and was counting the days till she might
reasonably hope to hear again. The promised letter of thanks from Mr. Collins arrived on Tuesday,
addressed to their father, and written with all the solemnity of gratitude which a twelve-month’s
abode in the family might have prompted. After discharging his conscience on that head,
he proceeded to inform them, with many rapturous expressions, of his happiness in having obtained
the affection of their amiable neighbour, Miss Lucas, and then explained that it was merely
with the view of enjoying her society that he had been so ready to close with their kind wish
of seeing him again at Longbourn, whither he hoped to be able to return on Monday fortnight;
for Lady Catherine, he added, so heartily approved his marriage, that she wished it
to take place as soon as possible, which he trusted would be an unanswerable argument with
his amiable Charlotte to name an early day for making him the happiest of men.
Mr. Collins’s return into Hertfordshire was no longer a matter of pleasure to Mrs. Bennet. On
the contrary, she was as much disposed to complain of it as her husband. It was very
strange that he should come to Longbourn instead of to Lucas Lodge; it was also very inconvenient
and exceedingly troublesome. She hated having visitors in the house while her health was so
indifferent, and lovers were of all people the most disagreeable. Such were the gentle murmurs of
Mrs. Bennet, and they gave way only to the greater distress of Mr. Bingley’s continued absence.
Neither Jane nor Elizabeth were comfortable on this subject. Day after day passed away
without bringing any other tidings of him than the report which shortly prevailed
in Meryton of his coming no more to Netherfield the whole winter; a report which highly incensed
Mrs. Bennet, and which she never failed to contradict as a most scandalous falsehood.
Even Elizabeth began to fear—not that Bingley was indifferent—but that his
sisters would be successful in keeping him away. Unwilling as she was to admit an idea
so destructive to Jane’s happiness, and so dishonourable to the stability of her lover,
she could not prevent its frequently recurring. The united efforts of his two unfeeling sisters,
and of his overpowering friend, assisted by the attractions of Miss Darcy and the
amusements of London, might be too much, she feared, for the strength of his attachment.
As for Jane, her anxiety under this suspense was, of course, more painful than Elizabeth’s:
but whatever she felt she was desirous of concealing; and between herself and Elizabeth,
therefore, the subject was never alluded to. But as no such delicacy restrained her mother,
an hour seldom passed in which she did not talk of Bingley, express her impatience for his arrival,
or even require Jane to confess that if he did not come back she should think herself very
ill-used. It needed all Jane’s steady mildness to bear these attacks with tolerable tranquillity.
Mr. Collins returned most punctually on the Monday fortnight, but his reception at Longbourn
was not quite so gracious as it had been on his first introduction. He was too happy, however,
to need much attention; and, luckily for the others, the business of love-making relieved
them from a great deal of his company. The chief of every day was spent by him at Lucas Lodge,
and he sometimes returned to Longbourn only in time to make an apology for his absence before
the family went to bed.
“Whenever she spoke in a low voice” Mrs. Bennet was really in a most pitiable
state. The very mention of anything concerning the match threw her into an agony of ill-humour,
and wherever she went she was sure of hearing it talked of. The sight of Miss Lucas was odious to
her. As her successor in that house, she regarded her with jealous abhorrence. Whenever Charlotte
came to see them, she concluded her to be anticipating the hour of possession;
and whenever she spoke in a low voice to Mr. Collins, was convinced that they were talking
of the Longbourn estate, and resolving to turn herself and her daughters out of
the house as soon as Mr. Bennet was dead. She complained bitterly of all this to her husband.
“Indeed, Mr. Bennet,” said she, “it is very hard to think that Charlotte Lucas should
ever be mistress of this house, that I should be forced to make way for her,
and live to see her take my place in it!” “My dear, do not give way to such gloomy
thoughts. Let us hope for better things. Let us flatter ourselves that I may be the survivor.”
This was not very consoling to Mrs. Bennet; and, therefore, instead of
making any answer, she went on as before. “I cannot bear to think that they should
have all this estate. If it was not for the entail, I should not mind it.”
“What should not you mind?” “I should not mind anything at all.”
“Let us be thankful that you are preserved from a state of such insensibility.”
“I never can be thankful, Mr. Bennet, for anything about the entail. How anyone could
have the conscience to entail away an estate from one’s own daughters I cannot understand;
and all for the sake of Mr. Collins, too! Why should he have it more than anybody else?”
“I leave it to yourself to determine,” said Mr. Bennet.
CHAPTER XXIV.
MISS BINGLEY’S letter arrived, and put an end to doubt. The very first sentence
conveyed the assurance of their being all settled in London for the winter,
and concluded with her brother’s regret at not having had time to pay his respects to his friends
in Hertfordshire before he left the country. Hope was over, entirely over; and when Jane
could attend to the rest of the letter, she found little, except the professed affection of
the writer, that could give her any comfort. Miss Darcy’s praise occupied the chief of it. Her many
attractions were again dwelt on; and Caroline boasted joyfully of their increasing intimacy,
and ventured to predict the accomplishment of the wishes which had been unfolded in her former
letter. She wrote also with great pleasure of her brother’s being an inmate of Mr. Darcy’s house,
and mentioned with raptures some plans of the latter with regard to new furniture.
Elizabeth, to whom Jane very soon communicated the chief of all this, heard it in silent indignation.
Her heart was divided between concern for her sister and resentment against all others. To
Caroline’s assertion of her brother’s being partial to Miss Darcy, she paid no credit. That he
was really fond of Jane, she doubted no more than she had ever done; and much as she had always been
disposed to like him, she could not think without anger, hardly without contempt, on that easiness
of temper, that want of proper resolution, which now made him the slave of his designing friends,
and led him to sacrifice his own happiness to the caprice of their inclinations.
Had his own happiness, however, been the only sacrifice, he might have been allowed
to sport with it in whatever manner he thought best; but her sister’s was involved in it,
as she thought he must be sensible himself. It was a subject, in short, on which reflection would
be long indulged, and must be unavailing. She could think of nothing else; and yet,
whether Bingley’s regard had really died away, or were suppressed by his friends’ interference;
whether he had been aware of Jane’s attachment, or whether it had escaped his observation;
whichever were the case, though her opinion of him must be materially affected by the difference,
her sister’s situation remained the same, her peace equally wounded.
A day or two passed before Jane had courage to speak of her feelings to Elizabeth; but at last,
on Mrs. Bennet’s leaving them together, after a longer irritation than usual about Netherfield
and its master, she could not help saying,— “O that my dear mother had more command over
herself! she can have no idea of the pain she gives me by her continual reflections on him. But
I will not repine. It cannot last long. He will be forgot, and we shall all be as we were before.”
Elizabeth looked at her sister with incredulous solicitude, but said nothing.
“You doubt me,” cried Jane, slightly colouring; “indeed, you have no reason. He may live in my
memory as the most amiable man of my acquaintance but that is all. I have
nothing either to hope or fear, and nothing to reproach him with. Thank God I have not
that pain. A little time, therefore—I shall certainly try to get the better——”
With a stronger voice she soon added, “I have this comfort immediately, that it has not been
more than an error of fancy on my side, and that it has done no harm to anyone but myself.”
“My dear Jane,” exclaimed Elizabeth, “you are too good. Your sweetness and disinterestedness
are really angelic; I do not know what to say to you. I feel as if I had never done you justice,
or loved you as you deserve.” Miss Bennet eagerly disclaimed
all extraordinary merit, and threw back the praise on her sister’s warm affection.
“Nay,” said Elizabeth, “this is not fair. You wish to think all the world respectable,
and are hurt if I speak ill of anybody. I only want to think you perfect, and you set yourself
against it. Do not be afraid of my running into any excess, of my encroaching on your privilege
of universal good-will. You need not. There are few people whom I really love, and still
fewer of whom I think well. The more I see of the world the more am I dissatisfied with it;
and every day confirms my belief of the inconsistency of all human characters,
and of the little dependence that can be placed on the appearance of either merit or sense.
I have met with two instances lately: one I will not mention, the other is Charlotte’s
marriage. It is unaccountable! in every view it is unaccountable!”
“My dear Lizzy, do not give way to such feelings as these. They will ruin your happiness. You do
not make allowance enough for difference of situation and temper. Consider Mr. Collins’s
respectability, and Charlotte’s prudent, steady character. Remember that she is one
of a large family; that as to fortune it is a most eligible match; and be ready to believe,
for everybody’s sake, that she may feel something like regard and esteem for our cousin.”
“To oblige you, I would try to believe almost anything, but no one else could
be benefited by such a belief as this; for were I persuaded that Charlotte had any
regard for him, I should only think worse of her understanding than I now do of her heart.
My dear Jane, Mr. Collins is a conceited, pompous, narrow-minded, silly man: you know he is,
as well as I do; and you must feel, as well as I do, that the woman who marries him cannot have a
proper way of thinking. You shall not defend her, though it is Charlotte Lucas. You shall not, for
the sake of one individual, change the meaning of principle and integrity, nor endeavour to persuade
yourself or me, that selfishness is prudence, and insensibility of danger security for happiness.”
“I must think your language too strong in speaking of both,” replied Jane; “and I hope you will be
convinced of it, by seeing them happy together. But enough of this. You alluded to something
else. You mentioned two instances. I cannot misunderstand you, but I entreat you, dear Lizzy,
not to pain me by thinking that person to blame, and saying your opinion of him is sunk. We must
not be so ready to fancy ourselves intentionally injured. We must not expect a lively young man to
be always so guarded and circumspect. It is very often nothing but our own vanity that deceives us.
Women fancy admiration means more than it does.” “And men take care that they should.”
“If it is designedly done, they cannot be justified; but I have no idea of there being so
much design in the world as some persons imagine.” “I am far from attributing any part of Mr.
Bingley’s conduct to design,” said Elizabeth; “but, without scheming to do wrong,
or to make others unhappy, there may be error and there may be misery. Thoughtlessness,
want of attention to other people’s feelings, and want of resolution, will do the business.”
“And do you impute it to either of those?” “Yes; to the last. But if I go on I shall
displease you by saying what I think of persons you esteem. Stop me, whilst you can.”
“You persist, then, in supposing his sisters influence him?”
“Yes, in conjunction with his friend.” “I cannot believe it. Why should they
try to influence him? They can only wish his happiness; and if he is
attached to me no other woman can secure it.” “Your first position is false. They may wish many
things besides his happiness: they may wish his increase of wealth and consequence; they may wish
him to marry a girl who has all the importance of money, great connections, and pride.”
“Beyond a doubt they do wish him to choose Miss Darcy,” replied Jane; “but this may be from
better feelings than you are supposing. They have known her much longer than they have known me;
no wonder if they love her better. But, whatever may be their own wishes, it is very unlikely
they should have opposed their brother’s. What sister would think herself at liberty to do it,
unless there were something very objectionable? If they believed him attached to me they would
not try to part us; if he were so, they could not succeed. By supposing such an affection, you make
everybody acting unnaturally and wrong, and me most unhappy. Do not distress me by the idea.
I am not ashamed of having been mistaken—or, at least, it is slight, it is nothing in comparison
of what I should feel in thinking ill of him or his sisters. Let me take it in the best light,
in the light in which it may be understood.” Elizabeth could not oppose such a wish;
and from this time Mr. Bingley’s name was scarcely ever mentioned between them.
Mrs. Bennet still continued to wonder and repine at his returning no more; and though a day seldom
passed in which Elizabeth did not account for it clearly, there seemed little chance of her ever
considering it with less perplexity. Her daughter endeavoured to convince her of what she did not
believe herself, that his attentions to Jane had been merely the effect of a common and transient
liking, which ceased when he saw her no more; but though the probability of the statement was
admitted at the time, she had the same story to repeat every day. Mrs. Bennet’s best comfort was,
that Mr. Bingley must be down again in the summer. Mr. Bennet treated the matter differently. “So,
Lizzy,” said he, one day, “your sister is crossed in love, I find. I congratulate her. Next to being
married, a girl likes to be crossed in love a little now and then. It is something to think of,
and gives her a sort of distinction among her companions. When is your turn to come? You will
hardly bear to be long outdone by Jane. Now is your time. Here are officers enough at Meryton
to disappoint all the young ladies in the country. Let Wickham be your man. He is a pleasant fellow,
and would jilt you creditably.” “Thank you, sir, but a less agreeable
man would satisfy me. We must not all expect Jane’s good fortune.”
“True,” said Mr. Bennet; “but it is a comfort to think that, whatever of that kind may befall you,
you have an affectionate mother who will always make the most of it.”
Mr. Wickham’s society was of material service in dispelling the gloom which the late perverse
occurrences had thrown on many of the Longbourn family. They saw him often,
and to his other recommendations was now added that of general unreserve. The whole of what
Elizabeth had already heard, his claims on Mr. Darcy, and all that he had suffered from him,
was now openly acknowledged and publicly canvassed; and everybody was pleased to think
how much they had always disliked Mr. Darcy before they had known anything of the matter.
Miss Bennet was the only creature who could suppose there might be
any extenuating circumstances in the case unknown to the society of Hertfordshire:
her mild and steady candour always pleaded for allowances, and urged the possibility of mistakes;
but by everybody else Mr. Darcy was condemned as the worst of men.
CHAPTER XXV.